Hi and welcome back to another video of
math skills to ACE chemistry for
introductory chem. Uh so in this video
what we're going to be looking at is
what is scientific notation. And if you
watched my last video on rounding you
might have saw that at the very end that
it was a different number format. And
the whole idea about this is it's an
easier way to do a lot of mathematical
calculations. It helps simplify them and
that's something that we'll see in the
future. So in this video, what is
scientific notation? Well, it helps
almost make simpler really really big
numbers or really tiny numbers. So that
way they're a little bit more palatable.
They're a little easier to plug into
your calculator and to solve them and
and to use them in different
calculations. So, well, what is this?
What do you mean by really big numbers?
Well, let me tell you. So, what if I
told you if we had the following number,
which is 602 with a lot of zeros, um,
probably bigger than any number you've
ever seen before. Well, this is
Avagadra's number, which is a very
common number that's used to count how
many atoms or molecules. And when you
see that, that's in its standard
notation. And probably the thing that
you see is what's what came to your mind
is, oh my god, is that's that big? That
is huge. Do we actually have to use it?
Do I have to know that for class? Well,
that's what scientific notation is for
to help make this a little easier to
handle so that way we can almost
minimize what this is. Now what it is is
it's counting the number of places that
you're moving the decimal. So there's a
couple little simple little rules that
we are going to be doing here. So let's
take a look at this and try to
understand. The whole idea here is that
the key is to write numbers as a factor
of 10. So let's start small and then
we'll go back up to that number before.
So if I have the number 500. Okay. Well
500. How can you write that in let's say
factors of 10? So how would you multiply
to get to that number? If I could do 10
* 10 * 5 would that that would get you
to 500. So think about it that way. If I
take 5 * 10, right? Which would be 50.
And if I times that by 10 again, well
that would be equivalent to 500. That's
the same thing. Now do I have to write
all these numbers out* 10 * 10? No. This
is what exponents are for. or powers. So
if we want to show that well we can
write different powers. So if instead if
I say oh 5 * 10 and being there are two
of those different 10 we can say 5 * 10
to the 2 power. So we can use exponents
to help say how many places we jumped or
how much did we move. So another way you
can show this is that 10 * 10. Well,
what is that? That's 100, right? So,
it's the same thing as saying five times
100. So, in the end, what how did we get
to here, which is scientific notation?
Let's write that down for ourselves. So,
that's our scientific notation. Trying
to block it with me.
Now the whole idea here is that all we
did was if I kind of like go to that 500
number we'll just write in the middle
is if we imagine that we have a decimal
here right it's not shown but there is a
position for it which is right over next
to the last zero and the whole idea here
is that we move that decimal place two
times right we went one two jumps which
represents how many factors of 10 that
you needed here. Right? So what that
told you is that oh when you wrote that
down you had your five
times 10 to the 2 power. So it helps you
see how many spots you are jumping and
that's how we write scientific notation.
So instead of us doing a five we're
doing 10^ the 2. So one of the simple
rules here when it comes to scientific
notation is that when we are writing
this down the the first number so we had
5 * 10 to the 2 power.
So five in this case is represented by a
that must be between 1 and 10. So 1
through nine right? So between so that
has to be in a very simple number right
you can count 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 it's
really easy to do and if you multiply
let's say 5 * 5 or 4 * 3 like those are
things you you have been drilled in your
head since like fourth or fifth grade
that's something that's always been
there. Now the 10 to the b part, well
that's the power, the exponential part
that tells you how big something is or
how small, right? So in the in the
current time, that's telling you the
bigness of something. So we're counting
how many factors of 10 or how many jumps
are we doing? So if I go back up to what
I had before, we can calculate how many
jumps did we have, right? So if I go
through this and we see that all right,
well, we go one 2 3
So 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20
21 22 23. So when we write this, we want
to we only write the significant digits,
right? So we have the 6.02 02. That's
your sandwich nonzeros, right? The rest
are all trailing. There's no decimal.
And then we write 10 to the 23.
And that's what it shows. So it shows
your significant values and it tell and
it helps you simplify
a giant number such as this. And that's
the best part is that it shows
significant values and it makes it
easier to look at. So what this is is
this is a number that tells you how many
molecules or atoms there are in a given
sample. So if you had like um let's say
like a small glass of water like a maybe
a shot glass and you had half of it
filled with water, this would be how
many molecules of water there would be
in that little shot glass. It was a fun
example. Um so that's the idea about it.
So let's try to do some like kind of do
some different examples. Um, so if I
kind of go down here and I ask you, all
right, well, let's do let's try one and
put it in scientific notation. So if I
have 1 million,
we'll put 1,4
00. And I asked you to put it into
scientific notation. Well, how exactly
would you do that? Now, the big idea
here is that you're moving that
hypothetical decimal point to make the
first number between 1 and 10. So, if we
see that, well, right here would be
between 1 and 10. So, the whole idea
here is that we're going to continue to
move that point. So, it' be 1 2 3.
Move it again. Four, five, six.
So we're just kind of bunny hopping
along the way. 7 8 9. So we move that
nine spaces.
So this would be 1 point. Now which
digits are significant? Well, that's
going to go to your last nonzero value,
which is our seven there. This would be
7 * 10 to the 9th power. So, not only
does it show only your significant
values, but it also helps make it a
little bit easier to look at and to work
with. So, if I kind of like, let's say I
expanded on this question and I asked
you, um, why don't you round the
following to three sigfigs in scientific
notation? So, the one that we just did
above, let's round it. So, if I said
round to the three sigfigs, how could
you do that? Well, we could count 1 2 3.
We're going to look over just like how
we did in our rounding video and we can
see well to the right of that last zero
is a four. So we round down. So what
this number would turn out to be is 1 0
* 10 the 9th
in scientific notation.
And if we want to put that back to
standard form, we could where we just
move that decimal place back nine spaces
to help show what the big
number originally was. So, as you can
see, it gets rounded and you kind of
lose some of the digits along the way,
but it helps it be in either standard
form or scientific notation form as
you're going through these. And the key
note here is when you're working with
these is that that positive number in
the exponent. So being that this is a
positive 9 for example, what that is
showing is that oh that this is a very
very big number. If I look at this
example down here, well, we can see we
move it 1 2 3 4 5 6. This would be 10^
the 6. That 6 is positive. We had to
move that decimal place left. So that's
letting you know it's a positive
exponent. If you have to move it left
going to scientific notation form, then
it is a positive exponent. It's a big
number. It's very, very large. So keep
that in mind. Now, what about small
numbers? We talked about big. What about
tiny? So a lot of times in chemistry,
we're talking about tiny amounts, right?
We're talking about atoms and molecules
and all these little itty bitty things
that you can't see. So, if in this case,
if you have your decimal number and
you're moving the decimal to the right,
I like how my P's going the wrong way.
If you're moving to the right, it's a
negative exponent. So, if we do a couple
examples here, so if I have 0.001,
so once again, our a value as we showed
it, it has to be between 1 and 10. So,
we're going to move that decimal place
one, two, three spots.
And we can see that we have one. And
being that there's only one significant
value here, this would be 1 * 10. And
being that you moved it to the right,
it's going to be a negative exponent. So
it's going to be 10 to the -3.
And that's going to be your final value
for that answer. We do the next one
where we have 0.0324.
Same idea here. We move that over two
times to show that okay, it's going to
go after your first nonzero number in
this case will be 3.24
* 10 to the
2 because we had to move that over two
times. And because we had to move it to
the right hand side, that shows you that
it's a tiny number. So it gets that
negative exponent here because it's
small. So this would be our final value
for that answer.
Um now just to kind of what's the final
summary when it comes to scientific
notation? Well, if we're going from
standard form, so seeing really big
numbers or really small decimals to
scientific notation, you move the
decimal until it's between 1 and 10. Key
word between, right? It has to be a
single digit in the front of scientific
notation.
The new number, let's just call it a,
should always show the correct number of
sigfigs. And that's the important thing
is we are always showing significant
figures. Especially if you're someone
that has to do general chemistry 1, two,
and maybe you're science major, you're
always going to be doing sigfigs
throughout your entire career. Even if
you're working as a health professional,
you need to show the correct number of
sigfigs when you're giving out medicines
and doses and all those kinds of things
as well. It's very important.
Now, if you write that time 10 the b
part or the exponent that counts how
many places you move the decimal. So, if
you moved it left, if you move it left,
sorry, then it's a positive value. If
you moved it right, then it's a negative
value. Sometimes you'll have to convert
it the other way, meaning that you'll be
given a scientific notation value and
you have to convert it to standard form
or just a regular number. meaning that
you this also applies to the backwards
direction or the opposite world. So keep
in mind that that trend that I've been
showing you this whole time about left
and right, it's not going to necessarily
apply. If you see a positive exponent,
that means that you're moving that uh
that decimal to the right hand side. If
you see a negative, you're going to be
moving it to the left. So keep in mind
of bigness or smallness when you are
coming across all these different
values. Let's do one example of the
backwards. So let's say if I had um 6.32
* 10 -6.
Well, this is a negative value. So that
tells you the decimal place is going to
be moving to the left hand side, right?
So it's going to be moving left. So or
sorry, I'm still pointing the wrong
place. So it's going to be moving left,
right? And so as we're moving left, what
that tells you is that we're going to be
going 1 2
3 and mean there's six here, right? So
we see a six 4 5 six places. So as we're
filling all those numbers, those are all
going to be zeros that are going to be
added in front of this as that decimal
place moves. So we can count that,
right? Okay, we have 1 2 3 4 5 zeros
that will be out front. So this would be
0.0000
63 2 would be your number here. So it's
showing you just to kind of even show
you cuz I, you know, misspoke that I
said there would be five zeros out
front. That's after the decimal. So just
to kind of show that right was 1 2 3 4
five oh six. So did I actually miscount?
Uh 1 2 3 4 five six. Oh I did right.
Okay. Yeah sorry I miscounted. So it
would be six places that that moved. So
when we are going through doing these
different um scientific notation values,
it's going to be showing this number
sigfigs. There'll be rounding involved
when you are looking at all these
different values. Okay. I hope this
video helped you and please stay tuned.
There'll be more to come within the soon
on YouTube here. Please like and
subscribe. Let me know how it all was
and let me know if there's anything I
can do to help you pass chemistry. Um,
this has been my math skills to ACE
chemistry and look forward to seeing you
soon. All right, bye now.
[Music]